Okay,
בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is כ"ו, chaf vav,
26. We start at the bottom of כ"ה עמוד ב'. chaf hey
amud bet. And the משנה mishna addresses itself to a case not
in the תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah talks about if somebody is
מקדיש שדה אחוזה, makdish sdeh achuza, a field of inheritance, and then
it's sold. So if he buys it back, then wonderful, end of
story. If somebody else buys it, then when the יובל yovel comes,
it goes to the כהנים. kohanim. What happens if הקדש hekdesh sits
on it and does nothing? The תורה Torah doesn't say. So let's
take a look at what the משנה mishna says. הגיע יובל ולא
נגאל. Higia yovel velo nigal. It comes to the יובל yovel and
still nobody has redeemed it, not the owner, nobody else. It's been
sitting in the possession of יובל. yovel. הכהנים נכנסים לתוכה ונותנים את
דמיה, דברי רבי יהודה. Hakohanim nichnasim letocha venosnim et dameha, divrei Rabbi
Yehuda. רבי Rabbi Yehuda assumes the כהנים kohanim are still going to
get it, but we have a problem. The problem is that it's
הקדש. hekdesh. If somebody else would have bought it, that would have
transferred the קדושה kedusha to the money. But it's been sitting in
the possession of הקדש. hekdesh. So the כהנים kohanim get it, but
only in this case, not in the case when it was sold,
then the כהנים kohanim get it straight. But here, it's still הקדש,
hekdesh, it still has קדושה. kedusha. So the כהנים kohanim get it,
but they have to pay the money. And the money therefore becomes
קדוש. kadosh. Now, I should say, you know, what's sort of not
clear according to רבי Rabbi Yehuda is what money? Do you do
it based on the fifty שקל shekel to the בית חומר שעורים?
beis chomer se'orim? Though the problem is that that's been constantly dropping
as it's getting closer to the יובל, yovel, so except the last
two years it goes back up to the fifty. So is it
the fifty? Is it the market price? Not so clear. If it's
market price, then it's not so necessarily so wonderful for the כהנים.
kohanim. You know, if I'm going to pay market price for something,
I don't want to be forced to do it and I'd like
to have my choice of what I'm buying. But if it's, you
know, if it's this fixed price, then it's still a nice deal.
So it's a little bit not clear according to רבי Rabbi Yehuda.
Do they have to, right? So they have to want to?
No, not so clear. That's also not so clear. Presumably the כהנים
kohanim of that משמר mishmar get it and how do you remove
the קדושה? kedusha? You pay the money. It doesn't sound like they
have a choice. I don't know, maybe they do have a choice.
Maybe they do, I don't know. Anyway, that's not clear according to
רבי Rabbi Yehuda. Somehow you need to pay money in order to
remove the קדושה, kedusha, but the degree to which כהנים kohanim have
a choice or how much the money is is not clear.
Okay, and we don't פסקן pasken this way, right?
I, you know what, I haven't checked the רמב"ם. Rambam. I see
the little letter here is right by that so maybe I don't
know. Okay. I can tell you that we haven't פסקן paskened anyway
for the last, for the last 2,000 years about this, so we
haven't actually acted on any of this. רבי שמעון אומר נכנסים ולא
נותנים. Rabbi Shimon omer nichnasim velo nosnim. רבי Rabbi Shimon says no,
they get it like as if it had been sold and even
though it has קדושה kedusha because it hasn't been sold, the קדושה
kedusha goes away once it gets transferred to the כהנים. kohanim. Okay,
so both of them agree that it's as if it had been
sold that it goes to כהנים. kohanim. The question is do you
have to pay in order to remove the קדושה? kedusha? רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says, you know, has a third opinion, completely different. רבי
אליעזר אומר לא נכנסים ולא נותנים. Rabbi Eliezer omer lo nichnasim velo
nosnim. They don't get the land and they don't pay any money
because he says basically, I mean the גמרא's Gemara going to ask
what the reason of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is, but basically רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is just focusing on the פסוקים. pesukim. The פסוקים
pesukim say if it's sold to another person, then when the יובל
yovel comes, the כהנים kohanim get it. So what happens if it
isn't sold to another person? Nothing. It stays in the possession of
הקדש, hekdesh, nothing happens, it remains הקדש, hekdesh, end of story.
So then the owner gets another chance?
Ah, so let's take a look. So then what happens? It stays
in the possession of הקדש, hekdesh, then what happens after the יובל?
yovel? So let's take a look. אלא נקראת שדה רטושין. Ela nikret
sdeh retushin. It's called an abandoned field. That's not really intrinsic to
the הלכה, halacha, but it just means, you know, that's its reality,
it's been ignored. עד היובל השני, Ad hayovel hasheni, until the second
יובל. yovel. Meaning, so now basically what he says is the תורה
Torah only provides for two cases. One case is the owner rebuys
it and the other case is somebody else buys it. Neither has
happened here. It's just stayed in the possession of הקדש. hekdesh. So
you don't do anything. So now you have another fifty years and
in this next fifty years the owner can buy it back and
somebody else can buy it back. And if so, then you know,
it'll follow the law of the תורה. Torah. Let's say it continues
to get ignored, okay, it's a really bad field. So הגיע היובל
השני ולא נגאלה. higia hayovel hasheni velo nigala. Second יובל yovel came
and it still wasn't redeemed. So now we're talking about, you know,
maybe a hundred years, okay, at least fifty plus, like I don't
know how much before the first guy was מקדיש makdish it. נקראת
רטושי רטושין. Nikret retushei retushin. It's called the abandoned field of the
abandoned field. Okay, so it's the bottom of the barrel. But still
the point is there's no, nothing that happens to it. The תורה
Torah only provides for what happens if somebody buys it or if
the owner buys it. If, and then it talks about going back
in the יובל yovel or whatever to the כהנים. kohanim. Otherwise, there's
no הלכה, halacha, it just stays in the possession of הקדש. hekdesh.
עד היובל השלישי, Ad hayovel hashlishi, until the third יובל. yovel. And
then the fourth and the fifth and the sixth. Nothing is going
to happen until you satisfy one of the conditions of the תורה.
Torah. לעולם אין הכהנים נכנסים לתוכה עד שיגאלנה אחר. Le'olam ein hakohanim
nichnasim letocha ad sheyigalena acher. What
if somebody after I don't know the third or fourth יובל yovel
finally decides to buy it? Then you'll apply the תורה Torah law
that when the next יובל yovel comes, then it'll go to the
כהנים. kohanim. But until that scenario occurs, nothing happens. Now there are
two questions. One question is now let's say the second יובל, yovel,
we did this and it's now in the second cycle. How much
do you pay? Presumably you do a reset. So now when there's
fifty years left to the next יובל, yovel, although one יובל yovel
passed, you pay fifty שקל shekel and then as it gets closer
it keeps on going down, down, down, down. You pay... Okay, so
that's number one, how you just figure the price. But the other
thing that's not explicit, which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
discuss, is let's say during the second, third יובל yovel *Yovel*, whatever,
the owner decides to buy it back, right? Does he then get
to keep it? Or then because it wasn't the first יובל yovel
*Yovel*, then it will go to the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*? The simple
sense of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* is עד שיגאלנה אחר ad she-yigalennah
acher, *ad sheyigalena acher*, when somebody else redeems it. Basically, the תורה
Torah. *Torah* provides for two scenarios: owner redeems it, owner keeps it;
somebody else redeems it, it goes to the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* ביובל
*be-Yovel*. And presumably, that would continue to be the two scenarios, no
matter whether you're in the first cycle of the יובל Yovel, *Yovel*
or the seventh cycle or the twentieth cycle of the יובל Yovel
*Yovel*. But we will see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
what happens if the owners redeem it after the first cycle. Yes?
Yeah, it seems to me to leave land in ישראל *Yisrael* just
abandoned like that is a פגם *pegam*. Right. And the...
it could be very, you know, dry land, very unplantable.
But whoever... whoever gave it to הקדש hekdesh *Hekdesh*, the קדושה kedushah
*kedushah* is its ruin. Right. Uh-huh.
You mean
by
making it holy, you ruin it? Because... because then you can't touch
it, and if no one comes and buys it, then it's abandoned,
it's not used, it's wasted. You're wasting this land that's in ישראל
*Yisrael* that's sanctified.
Right. But...
but... I'm not sure because clearly it's so easy to buy it
and use it, and presumably...
Well, yeah, but they're saying...
Yes, I understand, but I'm assuming that that's because it's a pretty
worthless field. Meaning, if this field had any good value, if anybody
could make money... normally, if there's money to be made, somebody's going
to make the money. So if this field was worth paying the
money and planting it, somebody would do it. So I don't think
it's because of הקדש hekdesh *Hekdesh*, I just think it's a reflection
of... if this was... let's say this was a very rich soil,
you know, soil-rich, very high-quality field.
Maybe it was too expensive?
No, but the whole point is the תורה Torah *Torah* sets a
fixed amount and it keeps on getting deducted, and that fixed amount
is presumably, you know, certainly not higher than market price, presumably it's
going to be an average or whatever.
Maybe there's a depression and people don't have money and nobody can
buy...
Oh, that's an interesting point. Meaning, okay, that's an interesting point because
maybe it's a case where there's a shortage of cash, and if
it was in your possession you could plant it and whatever and
you had seeds, etc., but maybe there's just a shortage of available
cash. That's possible.
Because if you're saying it's the worst of the worst... Yeah. ...then
why would someone give it to הקדש hekdesh. *Hekdesh*?
Well, that's what some people do. They're like, 'I'm going to be
very generous, I'll give this field I would never have used anyway
to הקדש hekdesh *Hekdesh*,' right? People will do that. That's a way
they can feel good about themselves.
Do they have to accept it?
Do they say, 'No, thank you'? No, actually, that's a good point.
No, they can't.
Like if you can give your old car, but if it's so
bad...
Right. And I tried to donate some books sometimes and nobody... and
they didn't want to take them. Right. That's a good point. I...
but you really can't though, because the way הקדש hekdesh *Hekdesh* works
is it's not you deliver it to the treasurer and they make
a decision to take it. You verbally designate it as הקדש hekdesh
*Hekdesh* without anybody else in the room and that automatically changes its
status. So that's an interesting point. But I really think that a
lot of this scenario will only occur if the land is not
at all usable. If it's usable and there's money to be made,
somebody's going to make the money.
We saw this before with someone doing something with the cow, you
remember the cow? And then you have to just let it die
because he made it הקדש Hekdesh *Hekdesh*, he made a mistake. So...
so it's another example of making some... sanctifying something ruins it.
Right. Although again, by the cow, I agree with you more. I
honestly think that this will only occur if the land is pretty
unusable regardless. If it's usable and there's money to be made, somebody's
going to redeem it and make the money. The only scenario I
could see where הקדש Hekdesh, *Hekdesh* created the problem is... is if
there's a real shortage... if the act of הקדש Hekdesh? *Hekdesh* is...
if there's a real shortage of funds. Okay, that I can see.
But... but... but otherwise, I think it's a real reflection of the
quality. All right, let's keep on going. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה *Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda*? What's the reasoning
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* that says the כהנים kohanim
*Kohanim* have to pay for it if it remained in the hand
of הקדש Hekdesh. *Hekdesh*? As I said, it's קדוש *kadosh*, so it
still... so it still has the קדושה kedushah *kedushah*. גמר קודש kodesh,
קודש kodesh ממקדיש בית *Gamar kodesh kodesh mi-makdish bayit*.
In the פרשה *parsha* there about sanctifying your field, it also says
if you sanctify your home. And of course, if you sanctify your
home, what happens if you sanctify your home? So הקדש Hekdesh *Hekdesh*
sells it, and the act of selling it is what... is what
transfers the קדושה kedushah. *kedushah*. So I'll just read you the פסוק
Pasuk *pasuk* because it's right there. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did not
take the example of בית *bayit* randomly. It says, ואיש כי יקדיש
את ביתו קודש kodesh לה' והעריכו הכהן בין טוב ובין רע
כאשר יעריך אתו הכהן כן יקום *Ve-ish ki yakdish et beito kodesh
l'Hashem ve-he'ericho ha-kohen bein tov u-vein
ra ka'asher ya'arich oto ha-kohen ken yakum*.
So you evaluate how much it's worth, you pay the amount, and
then it transfers. So the basic point is, like normal קדושה kedusha
*kedushah*, you don't remove the קדושה kedusha *kedushah* until you pay the
value. מה להלן בדמים *Mah le-halan bi-damim*, the same way there it
takes the paying of money in order to remove the קדושה kedusha
*kedushah*, אף כאן בדמים *af kan bi-damim*, same here. So it goes
to the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, but you have to pay them money.
But the... if he's comparing it really to the house, then it's
market value.
Yes, yes, yes. That's... you're right, you're right. The simple sense of
this is absolutely market value. In the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* it's unclear,
but the absolute simple sense of this is that they... For Rabbi
Shimon, and
what would Rabbi Shimon say, who says you don't pay any money?
גמר קודש kodesh, קודש kodesh, מכבשי העצרת.
He says no, there's other things that are holy that you don't
have to redeem and the כהנים kohanim. get, like the lambs of
שבועות. Shavuot. You could have done anything, but it's basically קרבנות korbanot
that the כהנים kohanim eat. So it's קודש, kodesh, the כהנים kohanim
benefit from it, and they don't have to pay any money. So
מה להלן בחינם, ma lehalan bechinam, the same way there they get
it without paying money, אף כאן בחינם, af kan bechinam, even here
too. Now there's a big difference. The difference is that there they
eat it while it's still קודש kodesh and they eat it in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and it has all these laws that
limit it. You can't let it wait till the next day. If
it's נותר notar you have to burn it. You can't take it
out of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Here, if we want it
to be my field, I'm going to use it for very secular
purposes. So the idea that it could remain קודש kodesh, and I
could benefit from it is not exactly the scenario. By קרבנות korbanot
I'm eating it as הקדש Hekdesh and it remains הקדש Hekdesh as
I eat it. Here we're trying to say I take possession of
it and it stops being הקדש. Hekdesh So anyway, let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara says. ורבי יהודה נמי נילף מכבשי העצרת,
VeRabbi Yehuda nami neilef mekeves haatzeret, why didn't Rabbi Yehuda learn from
that scenario of the lambs of שבועות? Shavuot? דנין קדשי בדק הבית
מקדשי בדק הבית. Danin kodshei bedek habayit mikodshei bedek habayit. Top of
כה עמוד א. kaf hey amud aleph. We learn things that are
sanctified for the temple treasury to the things that were sanctified for
the temple treasury. And if something is sanctified for the temple treasury,
the only way it becomes usable by people is if money is
paid to transfer the קדושה Kedushah off. ואין דנין קדשי בדק הבית
מקדשי מזבח. Ve-ein danin kodshei bedek habayit mikodshei mizbeach. You don't learn
things that are the treasury from things that are for the altar.
For the altar you can consume them while they're קודש, kodesh. but
things that are for the treasury, the only way you can use
them for your mundane purposes is by paying money. So if the
כהנים kohanim, want to use this land, they have to pay money.
ורבי שמעון, VeRabbi Shimon, and what would Rabbi Shimon say? ורבי שמעון
נמי נילף ממקדיש בית, VeRabbi Shimon nami neilef mimakdish bayit,
so that's a good argument. So why doesn't he, Rabbi Shimon, learn
from sanctifying a house or things that are given to the temple
treasury have to be paid for in order to use it? So
דנין דבר שמתנה לכהנים מדבר שמתנה לכהנים. Danin davar shematanah lakohanim midavar
shematanah lakohanim.
Because the difference is who is the recipient? When I sanctify a
house to הקדש and then they sell it and they take the
money, the money gets used towards the operating expenses of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash or for what's it called, like
structural repairs.
But when the field is sanctified, who gets it? The כהנים. kohanim
So let's learn from other things that כהנים kohanim. get. Every other
thing that כהנים kohanim. get, they get without having to pay money.
תרומה, terumah,
קרבנות, korbanot, פדיון
הבן, pidyon haben, ראשית הגז, reishit hagez, all those things. Some start
as קודש, kodesh some don't start as קודש, kodesh, but if they
go to the כהנים, kohanim the כהנים kohanim get them, they never
pay money. So therefore he says I don't want to learn from
מקדיש בית makdish bayit because מקדיש בית, makdish bayit, yes it's temple
treasury, but it's not going to the כהנים. kohanim ואין דנין דבר
שמתנה לכהנים מדבר שאינו מתנה לכהנים. Ve-ein danin davar shematanah lakohanim midavar
she-eino matanah lakohanim. I don't want to learn from something that's not
given to the כהנים. kohanim Now the point
is that in all those cases, either the thing was never קודש
kodesh to begin with, like the money for פדיון הבן, pidyon haben,
the מתנות, matanot, the ראשית הגז, reishit hagez, or if it was
קודש, kodesh. it was consumed under very narrow parameters and it was
consumed as קודש. kodesh, So they ate the קרבן korban in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash within a certain period of time and only
the male כהנים kohanim. etc. etc. Here, תרומה terumah
also, it's so fine, it's still as קודש kodesh. though. You can't
be טמא, tamei, there are still limits in terms of who can
use it, who can eat it.
It was consumed with its קדושה Kedushah status. Here, it was קודש,
but now you're going to use it, you don't want to use
it, there's not going to be any implicit limitation. You can have
non-כהנים kohanim. work the field, you can do it in טומאה. tumah.
So here, that is the conceptual problem here, that everything else either
it was never קודש or it was consumed as קודש. Here we're
saying it starts as קודש, but when the כהנים Kohanim. get it,
it stops being קודש. So that is anyway the position of Rabbi
Shimon. So you have Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon debating what do
you do, but they both agree again the Torah does not provide
for this case, but they both agree that the כהנים Kohanim get
it and the question is do you have to pay the money
to remove the קדושה. Comes Rabbi Eliezer and says Torah doesn't provide
for this case and nothing happens to it if it hasn't been
sold yet and the יובל Yovel. hits. So let's take a look.
רבי אליעזר אומר לא נכנסו ולא יוצאים. Rabbi Eliezer omer lo nichnasu
velo yotzim. They don't enter, they don't pay, they don't do anything,
the Torah does not provide for this case. אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah,
so said Rabbah, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר, mai taama deRabbi Eliezer, what's
the reason of Rabbi Eliezer? אמר קרא, Amar kra, because the verse
says, ואם לא יגאל את השדה, ve-im lo yigal et hasadeh, I'll
read you the actual verse. The verse says,
ואם לא יגאל את השדה המקדיש אותו, ve-im lo yigal et hasadeh
hamakdish oto, if you who sanctified it redeem it, then you add
a fifth and you keep it. ואם לא יגאל את השדה, ve-im
lo yigal et hasadeh, if you don't redeem it, you the owner,
ואם מכר את השדה לאיש אחר, ve-im machar et hasadeh le-ish acher,
and הקדש sells it to somebody else, לא יגאל עוד, lo yigal
od, then I lose my opportunity to redeem it because then when
the יובל Yovel comes it goes to the כהנים. Kohanim That's what
the verse says. I haven't redeemed it, הקדש sold it, then I'm
not going to get a chance to redeem it, it's going to
go to the כהנים. Kohanim So he says like this, let's read
what the דרשה drasha is.
אמר קרא ואם לא יגאל את השדה, Amar kra ve-im lo yigal
et hasadeh, if the field is not redeemed. לא יגאל עוד. Lo
Yiga-el Od. So basically you take the beginning and the end. You
don't sort of read the middle. If I didn't redeem it and
it was sold to somebody I won't get a chance to redeem
it again, we just say if it wasn't redeemed, meaning by anybody,
if nobody bought it, then לא יגאל עוד, Lo Yiga-el Od, then
we sort of jump to the end of the פסוק Pasuk and
we say then it does not have these normal laws of being
redeemed, which is a little funny because the point isn't so much
that it doesn't have the laws of being redeemed, right, it sort
of does in the next cycle, it's more like the—it's more the
point that it doesn't have the laws of going to the כהנים.
Kohanim. So it's a little strange and anyway אביי Abaye is not
happy with this. We'll take a read. ואם מכר את השדה, V'im
Machar Et Hasadeh, but however if it was sold, then והיה השדה
בצאתו ביובל, V'haya Hasadeh B'tzeto Bayovel, then it goes to כהנים Kohanim
etc. Meaning the basic point he's saying is that the provision in
the פסוק Pasuk? that says that it goes to כהנים Kohanim, is
only if somebody bought it. But if nobody bought it, אם לא
יגאל, Im Lo Yiga-el, then it doesn't have that whole middle scenario.
Now it is true that it's also
not that it can never be redeemed, but the point is that
that whole middle scenario of it going to the כהנים Kohanim. is
only a case when it actually was sold. So אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, wait I just want to read a little bit more, אמר
ליה—so Amar Lei the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye said this is a great
line, סכינא חריפא מפסקי קראי? Sakina Charifa Mafseka Kra-ei? What, you're taking
a sharp knife and splitting the פסוק? Pasuk So, not like the
גמרא Gemara doesn't do that many other times, but okay, sometimes the
גמרא Gemara takes some objection. What are you doing? You take the
first half and the last half and you're jumping over the middle?
What are you doing chopping up the פסוק Pasuk with like a
scissors and tape? You can't do that. So he doesn't like that
דרשה. Derasha. So he's going to have a different דרשה. Derasha. Now
before we get to his דרשה, Derasha, I just want to make
a point, which is I want you to read the first line
of
תוספות. Tosafot. מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? Mai Ta'ama D'Rabbi Eliezer? So you
see that תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר, V'im Tomar, ולא פשטיה דקרא
כרבי אליעזר משתמע? V'lo Pashtei Dekra K'Rabbi Eliezer Mishtama? That's what the
פסוק Pasuk is saying. The פסוק Pasuk, says if it's sold, this
is what you do for it. So if it's not sold, there's
no provision in the פסוק, Pasuk right? So תוספות Tosafot does not
really have, you know, whatever, תוספות's Tosafot's answer is not so satisfying,
but what's more important is the question that the—you know, אביי Abaye
takes so much offense that you cut up the פסוק Pasuk and
now we're going to spend the whole next of the דף Daf
trying to understand אביי'ס Abaye's דרשה. Derasha. The point is is that
you don't need the פסוק Pasuk to tell you do something else.
All רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is really saying is the פסוק Pasuk,
only provides for a case when it was sold. When it wasn't
sold, it's not in the פסוק, Pasuk. so you don't do—you don't
do any of that stuff. But for some reason both
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava assume that you have to somehow read
this scenario—you can't just say it's not provided for in the פסוק.
Pasuk. You have to read this scenario into the פסוק. Pasuk So
we're reading this scenario ואם לא יגאל. V'im Lo Yiga-el. That's what
רבא Rava says. If nobody bought it, then we don't do all
this middle stuff. Then it has a different law. Okay, but אביי
Abaye says no, then you're just cutting and pasting the פסוק Pasuk
and we're going to see אביי'ס Abaye's דרשה Derasha in a second.
Yes, Mike.
So how do we know that ומכר Umachar means the גזבר Gizbar
and not like, you know, maybe if I sold it to somebody
else, that's it, I can't redeem it, I've lost my right. What?
No, it says ואם מכר. V'im Machar. We're taking that to mean
that הקדש sells it. How do we know that? Well, I mean,
if you really look at the פשט Pshat of the קרא, Kra,
if I didn't—if I didn't redeem it ואם מכר V'im Machar or
if I sold it.
You're not in a position to sell it.
It's my—you know, it's—what
do you mean you're not in a position to sell it? You
sanctified it. Anyway, I don't understand how—no, no,
I absolutely think the פשט Pshat of the פסוק Pasuk is what
the גמרא Gemara. is saying. I mean, that's the gross דרשה Derasha
for it. ואם לא יגאל את השדה הבעלים ומכר את השדה לאיש
אחר הגזבר, V'im Lo Yiga-el Et Hasadeh Haba'alim Umachar Et Hasadeh L'ish
Acher Hagizbar, right? That's certainly פשט Pshat because you're no longer in
a position to sell it. You've—you've sanctified it. You mean someone else
redeems
it and then they sell it to somebody else and, you know,
it's sort of like, you know, with יאוש, Ye-ush, right? If I—if
I'm a מריה, Mareih, if I—I don't think—I
think the פשט Pshat of the פסוק Pasuk. is exactly what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. I only think the strange thing is what
תוספות Tosafot said, which is is that all רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
is saying is this case isn't provided for in the תורה. Torah
But the גמרא Gemara wants to insist that somehow the תורה Torah
is providing for it and telling you do something different. So רבא
Rava does it by cutting up the פסוק. pasuk: Let's see what
אביי—אביי doesn't like that. Let's see what אביי Abaye says. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא אמר אביי, Ela Amar Abaye, says
here's אביי, Abaye טעמא דרבי אליעזר כדתניא. Ta'ama D'Rabbi Eliezer K'detanya. The
reason is like we say in a ברייתא. Braita. לא יגאל, Lo
Yiga-el, it shall not be redeemed. This is if it was sold
to somebody else, okay, then he—the owner doesn't get another chance to
redeem it, it goes to the כהנים. Kohanim But let's look at
the דרשה Derasha of the ברייתא. Braita. יכול לא תהא נגאלת שתהא
לפניו כשדה מקנה? Yachol Lo Tehei Nigelet Shetehei Lefanav K'sadeh Mikna? Maybe
it should not be redeemed at all by him, not even like
a שדה מקנה. Sadeh Mikna. Now let me take out a minute
and tell you what a שדה מקנה Sadeh Mikna is. A שדה
מקנה Sadeh Mikna is not a שדה אחוזה. Sadeh Achuza. A שדה
אחוזה Sadeh Achuza is something that I inherited from my father or
father's fathers etc. A שדה מקנה Sadeh Mikna is simply a field
that I purchased. Okay, now what's the—what—the significance of it not being
a שדה אחוזה Sadeh Achuza is the following. Like for us nowadays,
right, what the heck do we care whether you—how you got this
property? Right now you own it, end of story. But in the
context of the תורה Torah and in the context of יובל, Yovel,
there's a big difference. If it's something that's an inheritance through—going all
the way back generations, then it means that if I sell it
to somebody else, come the יובל Yovel I get it back. Okay,
so therefore the fact that it's an inheritance means I'm going to
ultimately get this thing back. I can't really fully divest myself from
it. On the flip side, if it's a field that I purchased
from somebody, what does that mean? It means that I really didn't
purchase it in perpetuity. Right, essentially it's a lease until the יובל.
Yovel I only own it until the יובל Yovel. and then it—I
lose it. So there's a big conceptual difference between שדה אחוזה... Sadeh
Achuza... which is permanent and remains permanent even when sold, it reverts
to its permanence, and שדה מקנה, Sdeh Miknah, which is always temporary.
So let's say that so, so let's say, so if I מקדיש
makdish שדה אחוזה, Sdeh Achozah, then I can really have a profound
impact on it because if I don't redeem it, I don't use
my chance to get it back, it's going to completely transfer to
הקדש, which otherwise would never happen. When the יובל, Yovel right, otherwise
the יובל Yovel gets it back to me. Here, I can completely
lose it when the יובל Yovel comes if I don't redeem it.
Think about a שדה מקנה, Sdeh Miknah, however. If I have a
שדה מקנה Sdeh Miknah and I מקדיש makdish a שדה מקנה, Sdeh
Miknah, okay, I really only had rights to it for the next,
you know, 20 years until the יובל. Yovel So really all I
was מקדיש makdish was 20 years of use. So what do you
think would happen? I bought James' ancestral plot and it's 20 years
left to go to the יובל Yovel, and I was מקדיש makdish
it. What do you think would happen when the יובל Yovel, comes?
It just goes back to James.
Goes back to James. It doesn't go to the כהנים Kohanim because
I'm not in a position to permanently transfer the, the, the status
of this land. I only had it for 20 years. So I
can מקדיש makdish it, בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash can sell it for
its 20 years' use, or if they can't sell it, they won't
sell it, whatever they do, but at the end of the day,
when יובל Yovel comes, I never had it for more than that
and James gets it back. So there are two halachic differences with
a שדה מקנה. Sdeh Miknah. One is what I just said: when
the יובל Yovel comes, it does not go to the כהנים, Kohanim.
it goes back to the original owner. And the other difference is
is that the Torah, I mean, there's actually a מחלוקת, machloket, but
we פוסק pasken that you do not do the way you figure
out its value if the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash now wants to
sell it for the next 20 years and get some money out
of it, it goes by market value. It does not go by
the fixed, you know, 50 שקל, shekel, etc. So שדה מקנה Sdeh
Miknah has a completely different path. It's market value, it's only for
the next till the יובל, Yovel and then it goes back to
the owner.
Yeah. Almost like a lease. It was not necessarily really, it was
a lease. Right, it was a lease for 50 years.
Absolutely, and that is exactly the point. And that's why in the
end James is going to get it back because I never really
owned it. Absolutely.
The only improvements that are made on a piece of land are
only redeemed by the owner because like let's say...
No, you might have, yeah, it's not totally like a lease, you
know, but you, you still have rights to do structural changes to
the...
No, but then, but then let's say I want it back, let's
say after 50 years and I get it back and I'm like,
listen, take down your building. You put, you put a skyscraper there,
I want to plant my barley. It's my, it's really my field.
Yeah, I know, it's sometimes hard to understand skyscraper.
Okay, that is a good question, which I, which I'm not going
to answer now. But yeah, in general there's a question about, about
if I have sort of rights for, you know, קנין פירות, kinyan
peirot, you know, is it קנין הגוף kinyan haguf and to what
degree does that entitle me to make structural changes and so on?
But so it's a, it's an open question. I, we're not going
to resolve it right now. Anyway, let me just read the פסוק:
pasuk, ואם את שדה מקנתו אשר לא משדה אחוזתו יקדיש לה', Ve'im
et sdeh miknato asher lo misdeh achuzato yakdish l'Hashem, if you're sanctifying
just a field that you purchased, then וחישב לו הכהן את מכסת
הערכך עד שנת היובל, vechishev lo hakohen et michsat herkecha ad shnat
hayovel,
you figure out the time until the יובל, Yovel ונתן את הערכך
ביום ההוא קודש לה', venatan et herkecha bayom hahu kodesh l'Hashem,
then you pay the amount if you want to buy it back.
בשנת היובל ישוב השדה לאשר קנהו מאתו לאשר לו אחוזת הארץ, Bishnat
hayovel yashuv hasadeh la'asher kanahu me'ito la'asher lo achuzat ha'aretz,
and when the יובל Yovel hits, then what happens? It goes back
to James. It goes back to the original owner. Now, simple sense
of the פסוקים psukim sound like that you actually do the same
valuation of 50 שקל shekel and so on because it uses the
same phrase: וחישב לו הכהן את מכסת הערכך, vechishev lo hakohen et
michsat herkecha, right,
you figure out the ערך, erech, which sounds like again the same
issue about this fixed amount, but it's not clear. So there's definite
differences in the Torah. One is that it goes back to James,
it goes back to the original owner, I didn't have it for
more than that. The other possible difference is how do you figure
out the value? It might be based on market value, it might
be based on fixed value. Now, let's take a look back at
our גמרא. Gemara Okay, so לא יגאל, lo yiga'el, it cannot be
redeemed. יכול לא תהא נגאלת שתי
אלו לפניו כשדה מקנה, Yachol lo tehei nigelet shetei elu lefanav kisdeh
miknah, maybe it cannot be redeemed at all, not even like it's
a שדה מקנה, Sdeh Miknah, or meaning like a שדה מקנה Sdeh
Miknah in the sense that what happens when if I מקדיש makdish
a שדה מקנה? Sdeh Miknah? That when that I'm never, you know,
I'm never going to get it back and therefore it's totally sort
of out of my control. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, או, o, this
is very, I'm just going to read it and the גמרא Gemara
is going to unpack it because it's not so clear what it's
saying and the גמרא Gemara, is going to have to try to
figure it out. או, O, no, I can't do it anymore. וכמו
שהיתה
אינה נגאלת, Uchemo shehayetah einah nigelet, I can no longer redeem it
like it used to be, meaning that I, the owner, would redeem
it and I would get to, we're talking about a שדה אחוזה.
Sdeh Achozah. So I might have thought I can't redeem it at
all. No, it tells me I can't redeem it anymore, which means
I can't redeem it like I used to be able to. I
used to be able to redeem it and if I would redeem
it after I sanctified my שדה אחוזה, Sdeh Achozah, I'd redeem it
and it would stay in my possession. That I can't do anymore.
אבל נגאלת שתי אלו לפניו כשדה מקנה, Aval nigelet shetei elu lefanav
kisdeh miknah, I can redeem it like a שדה מקנה, Sdeh Miknah,
meaning I can redeem it and use it, but when the יובל
Yovel hits, I'm not going to be able to keep it. So
this is a very, you know, quick, unclear ברייתא. braita. It basically
describes some scenario where the owner can redeem his field, but as
opposed to the classic case where he redeems it and then keeps
it when the יובל Yovel hits, here it's saying you redeem it
but then you're going to lose it when the יובל Yovel? hits.
That's like a שדה מקנה, Sdeh Miknah, right, if I sanctified this
field I bought from James. There is some scenario where the owner
redeems it and he doesn't keep it when the יובל Yovel hits,
but he loses it when the יובל Yovel hits. So there is
some scenario like that. What is that scenario where he can redeem
it but not keep it? Okay, so let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says אימת, Eimas, when is this? אילימא ביובל ראשון,
Ileima beYovel rishon, if it's the first cycle when you actually the
owner sanctified it, אמאי איני נגאלת? amai eineni nig'eles? What does it
mean I don't fully redeem it? שדה אחוזה נמי הויא, Sadeh achuza
nami avi'a, it's like a normal field, that's exactly the law of
the field of inheritance that I redeem it and I get to
keep it. So if it's talking about during that first cycle, what
do you mean I redeem it but I don't keep it when
the יובל Yovel. hits? אלא פשיטא, Ela pshita, we must be talking
ביובל שני, beYovel sheini, that nobody redeems it during the first cycle
and now we're in the second cycle. Okay, now, ולמאן, ule'man, according
to who are we going like? אילימא לרבי יהודה ורבי שמעון, Ileima
leRabbi Yehuda veRabbi Shimon, if it's according to לרבי יהודה ורבי שמעון
Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon in our משנה, Mishnah. it doesn't get
to the second cycle. What happens if nothing's happened during the first
יובל? Yovel לכהנים נפיק, Lekohanim nafik, it goes to the כהנים. Kohanim.
So the הלכה halacha is, you know, it never gets to a
second cycle to have that discussion. אלא לאו רבי אליעזר, Ela lav
Rabbi Eliezer, we must be going according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
ושמע מינה טעמיה דרבי אליעזר מהכא, ushma mina ta'amei deRabbi Eliezer meihacha,
and you see his reasoning is like this, meaning how are we
reading the ברייתא? Baraita? We're reading the ברייתא Baraita as a scenario
where the owner can redeem it but he's not going to get
to keep it. What is that? So it's a שדה אחוזה. sadeh
achuza. So the first cycle he redeems and keeps it. אלא מאי,
Ela mai, the second cycle. Now according to לרבי יהודה ורבי שמעון
Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon you never get to a second cycle,
the כהנים Kohanim get it, but according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
כהנים Kohanim didn't get it and now you're in the second cycle.
So now, this wasn't in the משנה. Mishnah, What happens if in
the second cycle the owner redeems it? Since, right, and then the
next יובל Yovel hits. So it could be that in that case
the גמרא's Gemara, assuming that since you missed your chance in the
first cycle, in the second cycle yes you redeem it, but then
it's like a שדה מקנה, Sde Miknah, you're going to lose it
at the יובל Yovel and it's going to go to the כהנים.
Kohanim, Permanently or it just goes for a year and then you
buy it back? No, no, permanently. You lost your ability to buy
it back and keep it in your ancestral lands is only during
the first יובל. Yovel But doesn't the כהן Kohen have to pay
for it? No, that's the point. No, that's what the תורה Torah
provides for. If it was purchased by somebody and now you're somebody
just like some other person, then they get it straight. Okay, so
that's what the גמרא's Gemara assuming is that's where רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer learns it from, that they do this
דרשה drasha of לא יגאל עוד, lo yiga'el od, that there's a
scenario where the owner redeems it but then he doesn't keep it
when the יובל Yovel occurs. When is that? If it's in the
second cycle, the first cycle nobody redeemed it, second cycle then the
owner becomes like any other random person that he redeems it and
gets it till the יובל Yovel and when the יובל Yovel occurs
it goes to the כהנים. Kohanim Okay, yes. But doesn't the question,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said that if it's the כהנים Kohanim have
to pay and if they don't pay then it stays in הקדש?
No, no, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer didn't say that the כהנים Kohanim
never pay. The רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the תורה Torah provides
for two scenarios. Number one, the owner redeemed it and then during
let's say we're understanding the first cycle and then he keeps it,
end of story. Number two, somebody else buys it. So if the
יובל yovel? hits and neither of those scenarios occurred, you just wait
till one of those scenarios occur. So now it's the second cycle,
so the owner or somebody else buys it, so then the תורה
says fine, somebody bought it, comes the יובל yovel it goes to
כהנים, Kohanim no money. The only reason that there's discussion of money
by the כהנים Kohanim is when nobody bought it, so then the
קדושה never transferred. Once somebody bought it and paid money and the
קדושה transferred, then when the יובל yovel hits and it goes to
the כהנים Kohanim. they get it without, everybody agrees they don't pay.
So why did we say that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said that
the כהנים Kohanim, didn't get the land to begin with? Oh, if
nobody redeemed it. According to him, כהנים Kohanim only get it after
somebody has redeemed it. Okay? So there, that's the only case the
תורה provides for. But when somebody's redeemed it, because money was changed
hands and the קדושה transferred to money, then when the כהנים Kohanim,
will get it, they won't have to pay any money. Okay, so
anyway, so that's what we are saying now, that he learns it
from this idea that there's a scenario where the owner can buy,
redeem it but not keep it, and that would be in the
second cycle. ושמע מינה טעמיה דרבי אליעזר מהכא, ushma mina ta'amei deRabbi
Eliezer meihacha, we see from this, this is where he gets it
from. So the גמרא, Gemara although it seems like a pretty good
דרשה, drasha, the גמרא's Gemara, unhappy. ותסברא, Vetisbora, does that make really
make sense? רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון האי עוד מאי דרשי ביה? Rabbi
Yehuda veRabbi Shimon hai od mai darshi bei? You can't just say
ah, it's only going according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. לרבי יהודה
ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon also have to deal with
the עוד od in the פסוק, pasuk: לא יגאל עוד, lo yiga'el
od, which suggests somehow that there's some different status of redeeming and
you know, but there's still, and it's not just all or nothing.
So מאי דרשי ביה? mai darshi bei? אלא, Ela, we're going to
give a totally different explanation of the ברייתא. Baraita. הכא במאי עסקינן,
Hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about? בשדה שיצאה לכהנים והקדישה
כהן. Besadeh sheyatza leKohanim vehikdisha Kohen. So this is a field that
actually came to יובל yovel and it went to the כהנים. Kohanim.
So now you're saying רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer isn't holding... right, the
ברייתא Baraita does not have to be רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. You
had a very nice דרשה drasha that the ברייתא Baraita was רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and whether you described a very specific scenario, second
cycle, owner's now like anybody else, blah blah blah, but that doesn't
have to be the explanation of the ברייתא. Baraita. ברייתא Baraita could
be a completely different scenario. Now this also is going to be
a very specific one. Here's the scenario: I sold a field, somebody
else bought it, a קונה *Koneh* bought it, and it went to
the כהנים Kohanim. *Kohanim* in יובל yovel *Yovel*. Classic case. My field,
I sanctified, James redeemed it, went to the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* in
יובל yovel *Yovel*, classic case. I've now lost it, it's gone to
the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*. Now what's going to happen? Now it basically
has stopped being my שדה אחוזה sadeh achuzah. *Sedeh Achuzah* and effectively
become the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*'s שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah. *Sedeh Achuzah*. So
now the interesting question is going to be what's the status of
כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* if they מקדיש makdish *Maqdish* the field that they
got because it transferred from me? Okay, so ויצא לכהנים והקדישה כהן
kohen *ve-yatz'a la-kohanim ve-hiqdishah kohen*, and one of the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*
who acquired one of the fields sanctified, ועשו בעלים למפרקי *ve-asu be'alim
le-mifreqei*. So now is there any כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* here that we
can use this as an example? Joe's a כהן Kohen *Kohen*. Okay,
fine. לוי *Levi*. All right. So Joe will be our stand-in כהן
Kohen, *Kohen*. So I sanctified my field. James here, James here, my
שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah *Sedeh Achuzah*. James here redeemed it, he got
it till the יובל yovel *Yovel*. Then came the יובל yovel *Yovel*,
I didn't redeem it, it goes to the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*, it
goes to Joe. Now Joe sanctifies it. Okay, now very nice. He
is the new שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah. *Sedeh Achuzah*, but it once
was my שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah *Sedeh Achuzah*. I want to now
use this opportunity to redeem that field. You got the scenario? Now
that it's been sanctified by Joe and it, you know, can if
I redeem that field, can I get it back to be my
שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah *Sedeh Achuzah*? You got the case? It's a
good question. What? Why would you think you'd be able to? Because
once it's transferred, it's transferred. Well, that's basically the point. But let's
at least, you know, it's a reasonable question. Okay. ועשו בעלים למפרקי
*ve-asu be'alim le-mifreqei*. Now I'm trying to redeem it. סלקא דעתך אמינא
*Salqa da'atakh amina*, I would have thought, לא תפרוק שתהא לפניו כשדה
מקנה *lo tifroq she-tehei lefanav ke-sedeh miqnah*. And maybe I can't redeem
it at all because as James says, the תורה *Torah* says לא
יגאל עוד od, *lo yiga'el od*. Right, if I blew my chance,
I blew my chance. My chance was before the יובל Yovel *Yovel*,
I can never redeem it again. But what does never redeem it
again mean? Meaning, can I, am I not even allowed to redeem
that field to use it till the next יובל Yovel... *Yovel*? If
like that's it, you can never touch this field again, off limits
to you. That would be a little extreme. But if you take
the פסוק pasuk *pasuq* completely literally, לא יגאל עוד od, *lo yiga'el
od*, means I can never redeem it at all, not even like
a שדה מקנה sadeh mikneh. *Sedeh Miqnah*, meaning not even like a
random field. Is that really what it's saying? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar,
*Talmud lomar*, עוד *od*. No, I can't do it the way I
used to be able to redeem it, כמו שהייתה ונתגאלה *ke-moshe hayetah
ve-nitga'alah*. I can't redeem it like I used to, which would have
made it retain in my ancestral land. אבל נתגאלת שתהא לפניו כשדה
מקנה *aval nitga'elet she-tehei lefanav ke-sedeh miqnah*. It certainly can be like
any other random field that if Joe now sanctified, I can at
least redeem it and use it till the יובל Yovel *Yovel*. So
that's the דרשה drasha *derasha*. It's actually a very beautiful דרשה *derasha*,
right? It's more simple than the rest, although it's a very specific
limited scenario, it's more, I think in a way it's more simple
than the idea of the second יובל Yovel? *Yovel* in רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer* and so on. What it's basically saying is
don't mistake when the תורה *Torah* says that the owners can no
longer redeem it that they have absolutely no access to it. What
it means is once it's gone to the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*, it
means I can no longer make it back into my שדה אחוזה
Sedeh Achuzah. *Sedeh Achuzah*. But if I want to just redeem it
to use it till the next יובל Yovel, *Yovel*, that I'm entitled
to do. Okay, and that's what it means. And therefore it's not
relevant to the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? *Rabbi Eliezer*, to the question
about רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* about what happens if nobody's redeemed it.
Okay. And if Joe didn't redeem it, would it go to a
different כהן Kohen *Kohen* or would it... Yes, and if Joe did
not redeem it and somebody else redeemed it or whatever, then it
would be divided amongst all the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* in the next
יובל Yovel. *Yovel* cycle. Correct. Yes. Okay. Joe has now become the
new owner and you just apply the normal rules. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: והתניא *ve-ha tanya*, and we taught
והתניא *ve-ha tanya* often is used to make a little piece of
it. What? He gets all of a piece of it. Right. If
he was in that same, same משמר *mishmar*. It's only to the
כהנים Kohanim. *Kohanim* that are working during the יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
of that יובל Yovel, *Yovel*. So it's a, that is a job
to have, working in the יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* of that יובל
Yovel, *Yovel*. Okay. What if some of them would have the produce
for the whole year and it was just like a payment for
them for working in that? How long was a משמר *mishmar*? Just
a week. Anybody that was working in that, for that week, the
week in which the יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* of the יובל Yovel.
*Yovel* fell. So the produce of that field would be like a
payment for that work for that one week? No. Oh, they always
work as a group. No, you're just, you just hit the jackpot
if you're working for that week. You get all of the fields
that were sanctified and not redeemed by their owners. You don't just
get the produce, you don't work on the field. Yeah, yeah, yeah,
you're working in the temple. But you get the produce? Sure, you
not only get the produce, you own it. You get it. Oh,
I see. Okay. Once in a lifetime opportunity. Exactly. I can just
imagine the jockeying for that. Okay, anyway. יובל Yovel *Yovel* only happens
every 50 years. Right. Okay. So. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. Okay. Now, although you could, it's not so hard
to live through two יובלים *Yovels* because if you're born close to
the first one, you know, right, you'd be able to. Anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay. Now, התניא *ha tanya*.
Now, התניא *ha tanya* is most often used to as a challenge.
How can you say that? Didn't we learn in a ברייתא Baraita
*Baraita*? But sometimes התניא *ha tanya* is learned to just as a
support. And we similarly find in a ברייתא braisa, *Baraita* and therefore
this is going to be, this is what it means here, that
we have the same idea in a ברייתא braisa, *Baraita* that once
I have... lost control, I, it's not like I'm totally off limits,
but I can no longer relate to it as בעלים, as the
owner. Okay, so let's take a look. בשנת היובל ישוב השדה לאשר
קנהו מאתו. Bishnat hayovel yashuv hasadeh la'asher kanahu me'ito. So this is
talking about the case of a שדה Sedeh, מקנה. Okay, so here
the scenario is that I bought James' ancestral plot and I was
מקדיש Makdish it. What happens in the יובל? Yovel. Since as I
told you I only have rights for the next 20 years, I
obviously cannot take it away from James more than that. So comes
the יובל Yovel and it goes back to James. And that's the
פסוק: בשנת היובל Bishnat hayovel when the יובל Yovel hits, ישוב השדה
yashuv hasadeh the field reverts לאשר קנהו מאתו la'asher kanahu me'ito to
the one I bought it from, from James. And the end of
the פסוק is לאשר לו אחוזת הארץ la'asher lo achuzat ha'aretz to
the one who had the inheritance in the land. יכול יחזור לגזבר?
Yachol yachzor lagizbar? Now, what does it mean the one I bought
it from? Technically speaking, okay, actually there's a third person here. I
bought it from James, I sanctified it. Comes along David here and
he gets it from הקדש. What happens right? He paid הקדש for
it. What happens when the יובל Yovel hits? It goes back to
James. So the verse says what happens when the יובל Yovel, hits?
It goes back לאשר קנהו מאתו, la'asher kanahu me'ito, the one who
was bought from. Now, does it mean who I bought it from,
which is James, or does it mean the one David bought it
from, which is the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? So if you read
it very narrowly, the field reverts to the one who was bought
from, it could mean that it goes back to the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Now that's clearly not, as the end of the verse
says, to the one who has the inheritance. So that's just what
the ברייתא braisa here is filling out. יכול גזבר? Yachol gizbar? Maybe
it means the one David bought it from, which is the, the
treasurer of the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? שלקח הימנו? shelakach heimenu? תלמוד
לומר, the end of the verse says לאשר לו אחוזת הארץ, la'asher
lo achuzat ha'aretz, the one who has the inheritance in the land.
So therefore I bought it from James, it goes back to James,
the one who has the inheritance in the land. Now, it says,
so then just say that. יאמר לאשר לו אחוזת הארץ, Yomar la'asher
lo achuzat ha'aretz, just say it goes back to the one of
who's ancestral plot it is. מה תלמוד לומר לאשר קנהו מאתו? Mah
talmud lomar la'asher kanahu me'ito? Why does it say the one who
was purchased from? What is that adding? Why is that necessary to
say it at all? So to tell you the following scenario: שדה
שיצאה לכהנים ומכרה כהן. Sedeh she-yatzah la-Kohanim u-machrah Kohen. So we've got
now a different case, right? It was my ancestral plot like we
said before. James redeemed it, it went to the כהנים, Kohanim. now
Joe owns it. Okay, now ומכרה כהן. umachrah kohen. Joe now owns
this plot that used to be my ancestral plot, now it's Joe's
ancestral plot. Thanks Joe. Anyway, now ומכרה כהן. umachrah kohen. Now Joe
sells it to somebody. Joe sells it to David here. Okay, so
this plot used to be my ancestral plot, became Joe's because it
was sanctified and not redeemed or whatever. Now Joe sold it to
David. והקדישה לוקח. Vehikdishah loke'ach. And David sanctified it. You following this?
וגאלה אחר. Vega'alah acher. And somebody else redeemed it. So basically it's
the same scenario, it sounds complicated but it's really not so bad.
It's the same scenario of somebody sanctifying a field that they purchased.
The only difference is, is that whose ancestral plot is this field?
It was once upon a time my ancestral plot. But because I
sanctified it and didn't redeem it or whatever, it all of a
sudden now became Joe's ancestral plot. Okay, so you have the scenario
of somebody who bought a plot that was somebody else's ancestral plot
and sanctified it. We know in the יובל yovel it goes back
to the person whose ancestral plot it is. The only point is
there are two potential candidates vying for that, right? Joe, it became
Joe's ancestral plot but it used to be mine. And that's the
question: who does it go back to? Joe or me? Does everybody
agree that if the כהן Kohen gets it at יובל yovel, it
becomes their ancestral plot? Yes, that is the conceptual model. Right. That
and that is what we are sort of reinforcing in these דרשות.
drashot. To make it clear, once you lost, you the original owner
lost it as your ancestral plot because you sanctified it and didn't
redeem it or whatever, you're out of the picture. You are no
longer considered in any, no special status. And whose ancestral plot is
it considered? The כהנים Kohanim who received it. That is what we
are taking for granted and we are reinforcing by these דרשות. drashot.
Okay, so יכול, yachol, so in that case, יכול תחזור לבעלים הראשונים?
yachol tachzor laba'alim harishonim? Maybe I should get it? I could say
hey, I'm the real ancestral owner of this plot, it's going to
go back to me. תלמוד לומר לאשר קנהו. Talmud lomar la'asher kanahu.
That's why it has to not just say the one whose ancestral
plot it is, because then I
could maybe make a claim that that means me.
It says the one who was purchased from. And it means that
the most recent sort of ancestral plot is it was purchased from
Joe. He's the one who really has the status of it being
his ancestral plot. So the upshot of all of this is, the
bottom line is really very simple. If I did not redeem my
ancestral plot and it went to the כהנים, Kohanim, I have no
status anymore as the, as the שדה אחוזה.
Sedeh Achuzah? Okay, and therefore if I want to redeem
it after it was sanctified by the new owners, etc., etc., I
can, but not as an owner, just as a random person. And
it will revert to the כהנים. Kohanim, If it comes to יובל
yovel and somebody else sanctified it, I have no claim that I
should get it. I am no longer considered any special relationship to
this land. That's what we're learning. Okay, so now let's take a
look. ואיצטריך *Ve'itztraich*, and you need to say both even though they're
both saying basically the same idea. ואיצטריך לא יגאל ואיצטריך למכתב לאשר
קנהו la-asher kanahu. *Ve'itztraich lo yiga'el ve'itztraich lemichtav la'asher kanahu*. It has
to say the לא יגאל *lo yiga'el* scenario, which is the case
about where if I redeemed it after the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* sold
it, I don't have any special status. And it has to say
the לאשר קנהו la-asher kanahu, *la'asher kanahu*, which is if somebody purchased
it and then it reverts to the original owner, I don't have
any special status. דאי כתב רחמנא לא יגאל de-i kasav rachmana lo
yiga’el, *De'i katav rachmana lo yiga'el*, had it just had the case
of לא יגאל *lo yiga'el*, which is I'm coming to redeem it
and I want to claim maybe I have a special status to
redeem it now, דלא קהדרי כלל *delo kahadrei klal*, that where is
there it makes sense that I don't have any special status because
there it doesn't automatically go back. I only can have rights to
it if I actually actively redeem it. So maybe there we'll say,
you know, it doesn't naturally go back and therefore you don't have
any special status. אבל הכא דקהדרי *Aval hacha dekahadrei*, but when it's
sanctified by somebody who purchased it, that it automatically goes back, maybe
if it's automatic and it's not through an act of purchase or
whatever, maybe אימא קמה *eima kama*, maybe we really revert to the
way the good old times and the way things used to be.
Meaning if my only reason claim to get it is because I'm
now paying money and I should be like the original owner, that's
focusing on the here and now. And in the here and now
paying money, well you want to focus on the here and now,
here and now is you're no longer the, you know, the ancestral
owner of this thing, that's changed. But when it happens automatically, maybe
automatically there the whole sense of יובל *Yovel* is reverting to the
original way things are. It doesn't focus us on the here and
now and maybe it will go back to me. So it says
no. So כתב רחמנא לאשר קנהו kasav rachmana la’asher kanahu. *katav rachmana
la'asher kanahu*. No, once I've lost it, I've lost it and even
if it was sanctified by somebody who purchased and it will revert
to the original owner, I am no longer the original owner. ואי
כתב רחמנא לאשר קנהו ve-i kasav rachmana la’asher kanahu, *Ve'i katav rachmana
la'asher kanahu*, if it just had that scenario where it's sanctified by
the person who purchased it, דלא קיהיב דמי *delo kayahiv damei*, you
can make the opposite argument. There I want to get something for
nothing, so I want to just get it automatically. Sorry, you don't
get something for nothing and you're no longer considered the owner. אבל
הכא דקיהיב דמי *Aval hacha dekayahiv damei*, here where I'm prepared to
pay for it, right? Somebody else sanctified it and I want to
redeem it, I just want to redeem it and get to keep
it afterwards, but I'm actually paying, maybe if I'm actually paying, my
original status as original owner should be somewhat relevant. So תיקום בידיה
*teikum beyadei*, maybe I get to keep it permanently. כתב רחמנא לא
יגאל kasav rachmana lo yiga’el. *Katav rachmana lo yiga'el*. Sorry, no, you're
like a random person. Once it went away from your ancestral plot
and it went to the כהנים Kohanim. *Kohanim*, you have no more
special status. ואי כתב רחמנא לא יגאל ve-i kasav rachmana lo yiga’el,
ולא כתב עוד ve-lo kasav od, *Ve'i katav rachmana lo yiga'el velo
katav od*, if it just said לא יגאל *lo yiga'el* and it
didn't say עוד *od*, this is just repeating the previous דרשה *drasha*.
הוה אמינא hava amina, לא תיפרוק כלל *Hava amina lo tifrok klal*,
I might have thought that I'm not allowed to touch the field
at all. Right? If it just says לא יגאל *lo yiga'el*, once
it goes to the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* I can't redeem it, maybe
it meant that I can't even use it temporarily, it's totally off
limits to me. So כתב רחמנא עוד kasav rachmana od. *katav rachmana
od*. No, it just means I don't have the same status I
used to have. כדמעיקרא לא תיגאל *Kedeme'ikara lo tiga'el*, I can't redeem
it the way I used to, that by redeeming it I would
get to keep it. אבל תיגאל כדאמרן *Aval tiga'el kedamran*, I could
redeem it like it was a random plot of land and I
was a random person and I get to use it until the
יובל *Yovel*. So the upshot of all of this is, is that
after I sanctify the field and didn't redeem it and it went
to the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, then I no longer have any special
status as the original owner. I am completely a random person. But
don't read the פסוק *pasuk* to say לא יגאל *lo yiga'el* to
mean that I can't even use it till the יובל *Yovel*. I'm
not worse than a normal person and that's what the word עוד
*od* means. I don't have the same rights that I used to
have, but I still am like a random person and I can
redeem it and use it in the upshot. So you know, the
לא יגאל *lo yiga'el* means you really are, you know, that's the
whole... Alright, but that's the דרשה *drasha*. Yes, עוד *od* meaning, meaning
as you used to, as the same way, yes. And now we'll
be playing the part of Dave Wolf. Okay, so first of all,
by advocating the פרשה *parsha* this way, I mean there's obvious problems
with, with goes with the system of continually dividing up ancestral land
until, you know, you have a large population in a fixed space.
This serves as not only a way of redistributing the property but
also with some central control. It becomes the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* plan
that you asked yesterday, you know, it's not clear what the details,
who gets priority and so on, right? That some of these details
aren't spelled out, maybe because we're giving the kind of the regulatory
authority, I might say, to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beit HaMikdash*,
הקדש *hekdesh*, or perhaps the כהנים *Kohanim*, not the כהנים *Kohanim*, הקדש
*hekdesh*, in order to, to impose some kind of latitude or flexibility
within the system. I understand that, but the point is, is that
it will never, the only two people whose אחוזה *achuzah* it can
become are the original owners, meaning going all the way back to
יהושע *Yehoshua*, or the כהנים *Kohanim*. But I'm saying it never becomes
a, it can never become somebody else's אחוזה *achuzah*. Right, but it
can, but it can be taken out of the category of... Well,
no, because if it's taken out of the שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah.
and the יובל hits, then it transfers, it becomes the כהן's Kohen
שדה אחוזה. Sedeh Achuzah, Right? And then it becomes a כהן, Kohen.
so then they have the same rules as everybody else. Yes, yes,
yes. Right, so it's not like, right, you're right, meaning of what
you're pointing out is that the whole structure of all the שדה
אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah. doesn't work in sort of our very flexible commercial
society and this is maybe a way of whatever like, what's it
called when a when a museum gets rid of things, de-accession, they
have a fancy term for selling things. Anyway, but it's about taking
it out of this very weighty status and bringing it into this
more fluid. Yeah, but it's not true. The assumption here is is
that now that Joe got it and he was the כהן Kohen.
of whatever, and now he his relationship to it is as שדה
אחוזה. Sedeh Achuzah That, so yes, so you don't have that. So
he would also never lose it unless he מקדיש Makdish it. And
he was מקדיש it and didn't redeem it and da-da-da, then it
gets redistributed to the כהנים. Otherwise he would never lose it. But
right, otherwise if he buys it back, he's like the original owner.
And the כהן Kohein would also have the שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah?
status, get that שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah, status if it comes to
that. That is the assumption. Yeah. I mean, it hasn't been explicitly
spelled out in our גמרא, Gemara, right? I mean, basically רש״י Rashi
has been saying it all along. It's an interesting question that I
need to explore, which to be honest, hasn't been, you know, the
way רש״י Rashi has been reading in the spaces of what's been
going on is that it says it's now the כהנים's שדה אחוזה.
Sedeh Achuzah, But is it possible to read the גמרא Gemara we
just read, which is that it's nobody's שדה אחוזה? Sedeh Achuzah And
then what would happen if the יובל... or it's the temple's שדה
אחוזה. What would happen then if if Joe sanctified it and יובל
hit and you didn't treat it as a שדה אחוזה, then what
would happen? Then the כהנים get it. Then the כהנים so if
the כהנים get it again, oh, the only difference being the כהנים
get it as a שדה אחוזה. Like if if Joe says... uh-huh,
uh-huh. Or is it or can the כהנים sell it with a,
you know, instead of being... Yeah. Well, no, so the difference of
it not being a שדה אחוזה is that if Joe didn't sanctify
it but sold it, what would be the status of that person?
Would he keep it through the יובל? And I think the גמרא
Gemara, assumes no, because the גמרא, this whole scenario was, one minute,
it says, what's the case? Is it possible to think that it's
not the כהן's Kohein שדה אחוזה? That if after Joe got it
and let's say he sold it to David, that it's now, you
know, no special status, it goes back to nobody in the יובל,
it's just a non-episode. It's just like what happens in those times
when there's no יובל. But no, because one minute, the גמרא says
one minute, hold on, hold on. The גמרא says like this, no,
it says שדה, it says like this: שדה שיצאה לכהנים ומכרה כהן.
Sedeh she-yatzah la-Kohanim u-machrah Kohen. No, no, no, you can't say that
because the גמרא says exactly this scenario. It says the first wide
line, it says שדה שיצאה לכהנים Sadeh sheyatzah lakohanim ומכרה כהן. umachrah
kohen. So Joe got it, he sold it to David, והקדישה לוקח,
ve-hikdishah loke'ach, and David, you know, sanctified it. So it says יכול
תחזור לבעלים ראשונים, yakhol tachzor le-be'alim rishonim, תלמוד לומר לאשר קנהו. talmud
lomar la-asher kanahu. So the sense is what happens if it gets
sanctified and whatever, it sounds like it doesn't go back to me,
it goes back לאשר קנהו. It sounds like it's still going back
to Joe. His status to it is still as the שדה אחוזה,
right? According to what you're suggesting, David sanctified it, it would be,
you know, permanently in the possession of whoever bought it from הקדש
afterwards. Yeah, if he sells it to somebody else. Yeah, so the
simple sense of this גמרא, I mean the גמרא doesn't say explicitly
it goes back to the כהן. It says maybe it would go
to the original original owner, לאשר קנהו, but the implication is it
goes to the one who was most immediately purchased from, which means
Joe. So the simple sense of this גמרא, and that's what רש״י
Rashi has been saying throughout, is that yes, you don't you can't
get something out of a שדה אחוזה, but you can transfer the
שדה אחוזה status to the כהן. Okay, yeah. What were we saying?
Is it that רבי יהודה said the כהנים do pay, and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon said they don't pay. Right. But then when I
asked you a question afterwards, you were saying everybody agrees that the
כהנים don't pay. No, no, no, that's in a scenario where it
was actually redeemed by somebody. When it's actually redeemed by somebody and
then goes to the כהנים in the יובל, everybody agrees they don't
pay. Because then it was redeemed and money changed hands and the
קדושה transferred to the money. The debate is is that if we're
sitting in הקדש's backyard, I mean it's a field, whatever, you know,
הקדש has been sitting on it, and then it becomes the יובל,
that's where we're having the debate about whether they pay or not.
Because then money has never changed hands and the קדושה is still
on the field. Okay. Yeah. In my mind it was this question
about, you know, are there any parallels to when a man divorces
his wife, whether he's allowed to remarry her or not if she
wasn't married to somebody else. This idea that if the land goes
to another party, no, if it's not to anybody else first and
then you get it back first. Right. So that's what we're asking.
Well, according to רבי אליעזר, we're going to talk about that in
a minute, if it went into the second cycle and the owner
redeemed it, the original owner redeemed it in the second cycle, can
does he get to keep it or... Actually although it's very late
you will see the whole next Talmud is a complete repeat so
I think we will get to the bottom of the next page.
Let's take a look. Okay so the גמרא *Gemara* says like this.
מאי הוי עלה *Mai havei ala*? So okay that was all very
lovely. What's the upshot? Where does רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* get his
דרשה *drasha* from? Because now you have it wasn't the דרשה *drasha*
of לא יגאל עוד *lo yiga'el od*. That had to do with
the status of the original owner after it goes to the כהנים
*Kohanim*, that it stops being his אחוזה *achuza* and becomes the כהנים
*Kohanim*'s אחוזה *achuza*. So but what where do we get רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer*'s דרשה *drasha* from? No, אביי Abaye *Abaye* said you have
to use it for oh no the גמרא *Gemara* said that's not
good because you can use the דרשה *drasha* for something else. So
where what do we get רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*'s idea from that
nothing happens to it? אמר רבא אמר קרא *Amar Rava Amar Kra*
והיה השדה בצאתו ביובל *vehaya hasadeh betzeito bayovel*. The שדה *sadeh* when
it goes out in the יובל *Yovel* then it shall be קדש
להשם *kodesh laHashem* it goes to the כהנים *Kohanim*. בצאתו מיד אחר
*Betzeito miyad acher*. So what's so meaning then it sounds like Rava's
answer is really what תוספות *Tosafot* said earlier which is just פשט
pshat הפסוקים *pshat hapsukim*. It says the פסוקים *psukim* only provide that
it goes to the כהנים *Kohanim* בצאתו *betzeito* when it's leaving somebody
that somebody purchased it and it's leaving their possession that's when it
goes to the כהנים *Kohanim*. But if it's been sitting in the
hands of the כהן *Kohen* it's not leaving anybody it was with
the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* and it's still with the בית המקדש
*Beit Hamikdash* so the Torah does not provide in that case that
it goes to the כהן *Kohen*. So basically a simple point Torah
only provides it goes to the כהן *Kohen* if somebody bought it.
If nobody bought it then nothing happens and then you wait till
the next and then the כהן *Kohen* can't buy it from the
בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. What? כהן *Kohen* can't buy it from the
בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*? No he could. What do you mean he
can't? It just means the Torah meaning but but the Torah says
that when does it go revert when does it go to the
כהן *Kohen* ביובל *beYovel* if it's just leaving somebody's possession. If the
כהן *Kohen* is the manager in between time between time and the
יובל *Yovel* comes. Yeah. Oh the not not a random כהן *Kohen*
there's a particular כהן *Kohen* that's the that's the treasurer that's overseeing
all these issues. Yeah exactly. In between times and then when the
יובל *Yovel* comes he has to give it up. Exactly. Auction off
the well hopefully he did it before the יובל *Yovel* comes but
yes correct. So anyway okay so that's what we have. We have
that רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says look the פסוקים *psukim* say they
go to the כהנים *Kohanim* but only in a scenario when it
was sold. When it wasn't sold then you just wait. איבעיא להו
*Ibaya lehu*. Now they ask the question that the דף *daf* was
asking implicitly answered before or assumed before. כבעלים ביובל שני כאחר דמו
או לא *Keba'alim beYovel sheni ke'acher damu o lo*? When according to
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* you're now in the second cycle and the
original owners want to redeem it. Do they get to keep it?
Okay? Or do they only have a chance to redeem it and
keep it before in the first cycle? That's the question. תא שמע
ta shema, *Ta shma*. So now we're going to go through the
exact same דרשות *drashas* we went through before and try to though
use it to prove this point. לא יגאל *Lo yiga'el*. It shall
not be redeemed. יכול yakhol, לא תהא נגאלת שתהא לפניו כשדה מקנה
*Yakhol lo tehei nige'elet shetehei lefanav kesadeh mikna*? Maybe you can't redeem
it at all not even like a random field? תלמוד לומר *Talmud
lomar* עוד *od* anymore. כמות שהיתה אינה נגאלת *Kemot shehayeta einah nige'elet*
you can't redeem it like you used to אבל נגאלת שתהא לפניו
כשדה מקנה aval nigelet she-tehei lefanav k’sdeh mikneh, *aval nige'elet shetehei lefanav
kesadeh mikna* but you can redeem it like a random field. So
what does that mean? When can the owners redeem something like a
random field but not like their original field? אימא *Eima* what are
we talking about? אי ביובל ראשון *Iy beYovel rishon* if you're talking
about the first cycle אמאי אינה נגאלת *amai einah nige'elet*? שדה אחוזה
נמי הויא *Sadeh achuza nami havya* why can't you redeem it? That's
when you are can redeem it and it is your original field
and you get to keep it. אלא פשיטא ביובל שני *Ela pshita
beYovel sheni*. We must be talking about a second cycle and according
to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. ולמאן *Uleman* according to who? אי רבי
יהודה ורבי שמעון לכהנים נפקא *Iy Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi Shimon lakohanim nafka*.
There is no second cycle for Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon it
goes to the כהנים *Kohanim*. אלא לאו רבי אליעזר *Ela lav Rabbi
Eliezer*. So this idea that you can redeem it but you don't
have special status so now we're assuming like we assumed before what's
the scenario? You sanctified it the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* didn't sell
it you're in your second cycle and now you're waiting for something
to happen. Now you can still redeem it but because it's the
second cycle you don't get to keep it when the יובל *Yovel*
comes. What? We we did. So why are we asking? Because now
before we were trying to prove something else. Before we were trying
to prove רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*'s fundamental דרשה *drasha* now we're trying
to prove this question. It's going through the exact same דרשה *drasha*
just trying to prove something else. Trying to prove this question of
the בעלים *ba'alim* status in the second cycle. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says ושמע מינה *ushma mina* so that's what the דרשה *drasha* is
saying you infer from this בעלים ביובל שני כאחר דמו ba'alim beyovel
sheni ka'acher damu. *ba'alim beYovel sheni ke'acher damu* they're like a random
person because the whole דרשה *drasha* is that there's a time when
the בעלים *ba'alim* can redeem it but not like their original field.
So what would that be? That would be the second cycle according
to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says ותסברא *vetisbara*
does that really make sense that that's what the ברייתא braisa, *braita*
means? רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון האי עוד מאי דרשי ביה *Rabbi Yehuda
veRabbi Shimon hai od mai darshi bei*? That limiting the דרשה *drasha*
to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. What does what does Rabbi Yehuda and
Rabbi Shimon do with the עוד *od*? אלא הכא במאי עסקינן *Ela
hakha bemai askinan* what are we talking about? And now we're going
to go through the whole thing again that it transfers to the
כהנים *Kohanim* and then the original owner has no status once it's
transferred to the כהנים *Kohanim*. בשדה שיצאה לכהנים *Besadeh sheyatza lakohanim* it
transferred to the כהנים *Kohanim* והקדישה כהן *vehikdisha Kohen* and the כהן
*Kohen* sanctified it ואתא בעל למפרקיה *ve'ata ba'al lemifrekei* and now the
owner wants to redeem it and now he's claiming that he should
be able to redeem it as the original owner. סלקא דעתך אמינא
*Salka da'atakh amina* לא תפרוק שתהא לפניו כשדה מקנה *lo tifrok shetehei
lefanav kesadeh mikna* I might think that since it says he can
no longer redeem it means he can't redeem it even as a
random field it's too... Totally off-limits to him? תלמוד לומר עוד, anymore.
כמו שהיתה נגאלת, kemo she-hayetah nigelet, he can't redeem it like he
used to. He no longer has a status of an owner once
it transferred to the כהנים. אבל נגאלת שתהא לפניו כשדה מקנה, aval
nigelet she-tehei lefanav k’sdeh mikneh, he can redeem it like a random
field. He's allowed to use it until the יובל. Okay, so again,
rather than saying that when do you have a status, when does
your status shift? It's not according to Rabbi Eliezer when you get
to the second cycle. Maybe there if you buy it back you
are like the original owner. No, and your status shifts, that דרשה
is when it gets to the כהנים. Then you no longer have
your status, you can use it as a random field, but you
no longer have your status as the original owner. ותניא, ve-tanya, we
taught a similar ברייתא, braita now it's ממש mamash word for word
like we said before. This idea that when it goes to the
כהנים you are no longer the original owner. ישוב השדה לאשר קנהו
מאתו, yashuv hasadeh la’asher kanahu me’ito, יכול יחזור לגזבר שלקח הימנו, yakhol
yakhzor le-gizbar she-lakach mimenu, when it's sanctified by somebody who purchased it,
maybe it goes back to the בית המקדש? תלמוד לומר לאשר לו
אחוזת הארץ. talmud lomar la’asher lo achuzas ha’aretz. No, if it was
a field that was purchased and sanctified, it goes back to the
original owner. מה תלמוד לומר אשר קנהו? mah talmud lomar asher kanahu?
Why did it say the one you purchased it? Just say go
back to the original owner. שדה שיצאה לכהנים ומכרה כהן והקדישה לוקח
וגאלה אחר. sadeh she-yatzah la-kohanim u-macharah kohein ve-hikdishah loke’ach u-ge’alah acher. So
again, now it becomes what about the case where it was a
field that was purchased, but it was purchased by something that had
shifted to be the כהן's ancestral land? Because I sanctified it, I
didn't redeem it, it went to the כהנים, and now same scenario
except I'm now in the picture because it was purchased, the כהן
was the new ancestral land, but it used to really be mine.
יכול, I might think in that case, תחזור לבעלים הראשונים, tachzor le-ba’alim
harishonim, I can claim, hey, it's going back now to the original
owners, I'm the original owner. תלמוד לומר לאשר קנהו. talmud lomar la’asher
kanahu. No, the most recent original owner. It's a pretty funny phrase,
the most recent original owner, meaning Joe. ואיצטריך למכתב לא יגאל ואיצטריך
למכתב לאשר קנהו, ve-itzrich le-michtav lo yiga’el ve-itzrich le-michtav la’asher kanahu, and
it has to say both times that I lost all, I completely
lost my status. דאי כתב רחמנא לא יגאל, had it just said
I lost my status when it comes to actually buying it back,
דלא הדרה כלל, de-lo hadrah klal, there because it didn't happen automatically,
so maybe I'm just focusing on buying it back, now I'm nobody.
כתב רחמנא לאשר קנהו. kasav rachmana la’asher kanahu. Therefore it had to
say, I'm sorry, did I skip a line? What do you mean
by דלא הדרה כלל? de-lo hadrah klal? Meaning it doesn't go back
automatically. Okay, but maybe in the case where it goes back automatically,
like when it was sanctified by the one who purchased it and
it automatically goes back to the original owner, maybe then I can
claim my original status? כתב רחמנא לאשר קנהו. No, even in that
case not. ואי כתב רחמנא לאשר קנהו, if it just said in
that case I don't have my original status, that's because I want
something for nothing, דקאתי בלא דמי, de-ka’ati be-lo damei, I'm not paying,
you know, Dave is sanctified it, he purchased it, and I want
to get it automatically. אבל היכא דקאתי בדמי, aval heicha de-ka’ati be-damei,
when I'm actually paying for it, I'm redeeming it, but all I
want to do is I want to redeem it and keep it,
but I'm actually paying for it, דתקום בידייהו, de-teikum be-yadeihu, I might
think that that entitles me to claim my original status and to
keep it even when the יובל hits. כתב רחמנא לא יגאל. It
says, therefore it says even there you can't redeem it like the
original owner. ואי כתב רחמנא לא יגאל, and if it didn't have
the word עוד, it just says I can't redeem it period, full
stop, ולא כתב עוד, and it didn't say עוד, הוה אמינא, hava
amina I would have thought לא תיפרק כלל, lo tiparek klal, that
it's totally off-limits to me. Once it transferred to be Joe's ancestral
land, I'm not just like a random person, I'm a no, I'm
off, it's off-limits, I can never redeem it. So no, כתב רחמנא
עוד. Therefore it says I can't redeem it like I used to.
כמו שהיתה נגאלת, kemo she-hayetah nigelet, I can't redeem it with a
status of the original owner. אבל נגאלת שתהא לפניו כשדה מקנה, but
I can redeem it like it's a random field, and therefore if
what if, you know, it transferred to Joe and he sanctified it,
I can redeem it and use it until the יובל. I can't
redeem it as my with my original status that I keep it
when the יובל comes, but I can redeem it like a random
field. Okay, good. So what we have said is clearly when it
transfers to the כהנים, I lose my status as the original owner,
it becomes the כהנים become the original owners now, and that's for
all the different הלכות halachos where original owners matter. And the one
unresolved question is according to Rabbi Eliezer, if it's not redeemed by
anybody and therefore the יובל didn't do anything to it, and now
it gets and now comes the second cycle and I want to
redeem it, can I still then can I claim still my status
as the original owner once the יובל passed? And then will I
be able to keep it back, get it back into my ancestral
lands? So מאי הוה עלה, mai hava alah, what was the upshot
answer to that question? So תא שמע, let's learn it from our
משנה. Mishnah רבי אליעזר אומר גאלה בעלים ביובל שני יוצא לכהנים ביובל.
Rabbi Eliezer omer ga’alah ba’alim be-yovel sheni, yotzei la-kohanim be-yovel. Here we
have an explicit ברייתא, braita not our משנה, Mishnah we're going to
get to our משנה Mishnah. in a minute. An explicit ברייתא braita.
that Rabbi Eliezer says if the owner redeems it in the second
יובל, it goes to the כהנים. So you see I lost my
status. My only option to get it back into my ancestral plots
is the first cycle. So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei
Ravina le-Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
it's very nice you have a ברייתא, braita, but our משנה Mishnah
sounds like the opposite. הא נן לא תנן הכי, ha nan lo
tenan hachi, that's not our משנה. mishna, What does our משנה mishna.
say? רבי אליעזר אומר אין הכהנים נכנסים לתוכה, Rabbi Eliezer omer ein
ha-kohanim nichnasin le-tochah, the כהנים will never get this land if it
passed, you know, even if you're in the second, third, fourth, fifth
cycle, עד שיגאלנה אחר, until an another person redeems it. So the
implication... It could be the 10th cycle, but the provision in the
Torah that it goes to the כהנים is only when somebody else
redeems it. But he said somebody else! So presumably the owner if
he redeems it gets to keep it. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
he said, so he said, you know what? בעלים ביובל שני כאחר
דמו. ba'alim beyovel sheni ka'acher damu. It's all a question of definition.
By the time you get to the second cycle, the import of
the יובל is something did not revert to you in the first
יובל, that means that you're no longer considered the owner. So therefore,
yes, somebody else redeems it, but by the time you're in the
second cycle, you're now somebody else. Okay, and you understand the logic.
The logic is, I know it's not פשט in the משנה, mishna.
yes, but the logic is, if you didn't get it back when
the יובל hits, then that shows that you're not the owner anymore.
You're no longer considered the original owner. Let's just finish the משנה.
mishna. איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, now some people say this discussion happened
in the reverse. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, גאלה ביובל שני
אינה יוצא לכהנים ביובל. ga'ala beyovel sheni eina yotza lakohanim beyovel. That
the ברייתא said the opposite. The ברייתא said that if the original
owner redeemed it in the second cycle, he does get to keep
it. Okay, he does retain his status. So אמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי, amar lei Ravina leRav Ashi, אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan
nami tanina. That's our משנה. mishna, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer,
אין הכהנים נכנסים לתוכה עד שיגאלנה אחר. ein hakohanim nichnasim letoka ad
sheyigalena acher. That the only way it goes to כהנים is if
another person redeems it in a later cycle, which implies that if
the owner still retains his status. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said,
well, you can't prove it from the משנה. mishna, אי מתניתין, iy
matnitin, הוה אמינא בעלים ביובל שני כאחר דמו. If it was just
the משנה, mishna, I don't know, maybe by the second cycle the
owner is considered another person, not he's completely lost his status. So
it's not clear from the משנה, but it is clear from the
ברייתא. גמרא דעבדה כזה וכזה. gemara de'avda kizeh vekizeh. Right. So the
point is, at the end of the day, you can't prove it
from the משנה, and you have two different versions of the ברייתא,
so we don't know what the answer is. What is the status
of the owner in the second cycle according to רבי אליעזר?